Lucas Oliveira

lcastro.oliveira@gmail.com

Summary

Currently an intern in Web Development at EITS IT with head office inside Itaipu Technology Park(PTI[Portuguese]). I'm on my senior year(Computer Science B.A) at the Western Paraná State Public University, Brazil. I also was an exchange student who took lectures in Cloud Computing and Cyber security at the University of Waikato, New Zealand. After finishing my studying abroad period I moved to Wairoa, Hawkes Bay in order to take a three month summer internship at the town's district council. There I had the opportunity to work on the development of an mobile application for Android that is still on progress. Before that I interned at the system development division at Itaipu binational dam (http://www.itaipu.gov.br/en), the world's largest generator of renewable and clean energy, from January 2012 to December 2013. I focused on development of small and medium sized computational solutions in order to supply operational demand from the human resources department. I have experience with BEA Weblogic 8.1 framework, an early version of the current Oracle Weblogic, which uses Java EE underneath. I have done some projects in PHP as well, mostly using a tool based on PRADO framework.

Experience

Web Development Intern at EITS IT Solutions

March 2015 - Present (9 months)

Full Stack Web developer. Technologies I work with: Hibernate, Spring Framework, Angular JS e Angular Material.

Summer Intern at Wairoa District Council

December 2014 - February 2015 (3 months)

Volunteer summer internship. Involved helping the Wairoa community in I.T solutions. Brief introduction to geographic information systems(GIS) along with the opportunity to develop a project in Android.

Intern at Itaipu Binacional

January 2012 - December 2013 (2 years)

Intern at the system development division(Brazilian side), focusing on development of small business solutions for the HR division, as well as providing perfective and corrective maintenance for enterprise level systems.

English Teacher at Wizard Idiomas, Unidade Foz do Iguaçu

August 2010 - January 2011 (6 months)

Classes taught for adults at beginner level.

Education

Universidade Estadual do Oeste do Paraná

Bachelor's degree, Computer Science, 2010 - 2015

University of Waikato

1 year free paper credit in Computer Science, 2014 - 2014

Activities and Societies: University of Waikato Tramping Club

Projects

Information Technology Master Plan - Brazilian Navy

March 2015 to Present

Members:Lucas Oliveira, Henrique Lobato Zago, Priscyla Marçal Anacleto

A project for the Brazilian navy's supply chain directory board(DAbM in Portuguese). Development of a system that automatically creates an Information Technology Master Plan based on input given by the group of users. This system enables the registration of textual information, IT strategies, principles and guidelines, IT necessities and it's goals, activities and expected budget. With all these information, the system generates a document in PDF format with all the data structured in a specific topic order defined by any user. For this project, the used technologies and tools were Spring framework for back end + AngularJS and Material design at the front end. Furthermore, there was an extensive use of tools such as DynamicReports and JasperReports for the creation of dynamic reports and export to PDF format.

GoDiscover - Android application proof of concept

January 2015 to Present

Members:Lucas Oliveira, Lucas Nathan Barbosa de Oliveira, Ian Nícolas Lemes Alves

Development of a mobile application for the Wairoa community. Used by local authorities and the general public with the purpose to stimulate dissemination of the district's region touristic and historic information. As a proof of concept, information such as photos, videos and curiosities about the the walkway were collected with the town's museum curators. Using gamification concepts, the app user only has access to those information only if he/she scans any QR codes that are spread across some spots in the walkway. Therefore, making the app a motivation to its user's to explore the places along the area. Project's technical features: Content in modules. Tracks, itineraries and tours may be created online and download onto the app. This architecture, using cloud computing, makes the application more robust and flexible. This was obtained using Amazon Web Services(AWS), where all the content created by a support web site is sent to the storage service(Amazon S3).

Registration System for Contracts

July 2013 to December 2013

Members:Lucas Oliveira

Development of a system responsible for the registration of documents and contracts to be used for the coordination division at Itaipu. Using LAPSI framework, a customized version of PRADO PHP (http://www.pradosoft.com/) created by the company's analysts handle their own demand. Basically the system

is in charge of keeping track of the contracts, its addendum and measurements between Itaipu and other companies.

SQL Query Optimization for Automatic Reports Generation

February 2013 to May 2013

Members:Lucas Oliveira

Work involving the detailed study of complex SQL queries used to obtain the raw data that serve as input for the Jasper reports generator, known as iReport. It was required to do corrective maintenance on the data retrieval process of two reports since their data capture was very slow, not properly meeting the final user's needs, in addition to overloading the IT infrastructure. After a careful analysis of commands passed to the database and applying concepts of relational algebra, I was able to modify instructions input and get the same set of information much more quickly. The results obtained in the development environment were satisfactory. For one report there was an improvement between 5x and 6x of average execution speed. In another report, it was possible to increase performance by more than 200x. Although the solution was simple, just modify one single line of code among five hundred, this is my favorite project at Itaipu. It was a good example where I could apply on concepts learned in lectures in a career setting.

Integrated Benefits Management System Perfective Maintenance

May 2012 to June 2012

Members:Lucas Oliveira, Cláudio José Fernandes

Enhancement system maintenance responsible for making new fields of registration for Itaipu employees and their families. Going through a complete development cycle: from adjustments in the documentation, web page prototyping, adaptations on both application's web and business tiers, modifying the SQL responsible for acquiring data to the report generator, along with end-user feedback and bug fix. This project was interesting because although the changes were very small, they have given me a greater understanding of the stages of an enterprise software development process as a whole, in addition to other tools and procedures necessary for the developers, like systematic application deployment in development, test and production servers and use of repositories which for this project was SVN. Although aware of the importance of GIT.

Query Service for Medical Procedures Coverage

April 2012 to May 2012

Members:Lucas Oliveira

The development process arose from the need to facilitate obtaining information for healthcare professionals and employees of Itaipu about which procedures are covered by PAMHO (Itaipu Health Care Plan Insurance). If these procedures need expertise, individual analysis or a more bureaucratic course of action. The aim of the service is to allow a doctor, before prescribing the procedures to a user's plan, already have conditions to know whether it is covered or not. In addition, the service should be able to tell if the patient needs to fill additional forms and send it to analysis by the company, along with other information if necessary. It also helps the company's benefits department, decreasing the number of consultations on this information. The necessary data was already available in a spreadsheet and the development cycle needed to be as short as possible, I was instructed to make a Java program that could access the document, navigate through it and find all the information needed for a particular query (instead of converting the spreadsheet

to a database). For this project I used the POI libraries, maintained by Apache. It provides the necessary mechanisms for a Java application to handle Office documents (such as .doc, .xls, .ppt etc...). I've created a simple linear search algorithm that was responsible for determining the search area of the worksheet, ignore unnecessary data as headers and human only sensitive information and set a proper stop condition. Inherent difficulties of the project were found and solved as much as possible. This project was interesting because it was my first contact with web programming, being my first experience working with technologies like HTML, CSS, JavaScript and Servlets, in addition to Apache POI libraries.

Certifications

Oracle Certified Professional, Java SE 6 Programmer

License 240144027OCPJSE6P August 2015

Learn and Understand AngularJS

November 2015

Computer Networks

March 2013

Web Intelligence and Big Data

June 2013

Introduction to Psychology

July 2013

Skills & Expertise

Java

UML

SQL

Linux

Weblogic

JavaScript

BEA

Android

Amazon Web Services

Spring Framework

Hibernate

AngularJS

Jasper Reports

MySQL

PHP

CSS

Desenvolvimento de sites

Engenharia de software

Servidor Apache

Padrões de design

Banco de dados

Oracle 8i-11g

Java Enterprise Edition HTML

Courses

English Teacher

Wizard Idiomas, Unidade Foz do Iguaçu

English

Independent Coursework

Java Programming 500+ workload

Languages

Portuguese (Native or bilingual proficiency)

English (Native or bilingual proficiency)

Spanish (Elementary proficiency)

Interests

Software Engineering, Mobile Development, Design Patterns, Computer Networks, Master/PhD Degree Programs and Scholarships, Big Data, Map Reduce, Quantum Computing, Psychology, Sci-Fi, Guitars, Tramping, Travelling.

Publications

Serviço de Consulta On-line a Procedimentos Médicos Utilizando Planilha Eletrônica como Base de Dados

I Congresso de Tecnologias, Engenharias e Ciências Exatas August 7, 2013

Authors: Lucas Oliveira, Claudio José Fernandes

Algoritmos de Percurso Aplicados à Robótica

II Congresso de Tecnologias, Engenharias e Ciências Exatas November 5, 2015

Authors: Lucas Oliveira, Teresinha Arnauts Hachisuca

Honors and Awards

Honorary Citizenship of Wairoa

His Worship the Mayor Craig Little

February 2015

Science Without Borders Scholarship

Brazilian Ministry of Education(MEC)

October 2013

Test Scores

Test Of English as a Foreign Language (TOEFL iBT)

June 2013 Score:107

Test of English for International Communication (TOEIC)

January 2010 Score:855

Organizations

Association for Computing Machinery - Student member

April 2013 to Present

Lucas Oliveira

lcastro.oliveira@gmail.com



Contact Lucas on LinkedIn